<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Exact journal of the siege of Namur giving a particular account of the several sallies and attacks, and other most remarkable passages from the first investing of the place : together with the articles of capitulation, both for surrendring the city and castle.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38922</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3648</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8666</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13255434</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13255434</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98680</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38922)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98680)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 453:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Exact journal of the siege of Namur giving a particular account of the several sallies and attacks, and other most remarkable passages from the first investing of the place : together with the articles of capitulation, both for surrendring the city and castle.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Whitlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Namur (Belgium) --  History --  Siege, 1695.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Military --  1603-1714 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:98680:1"/>
            <p>AN EXACT JOURNAL OF THE SIEGE OF Namur, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98680:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98680:2"/>
            <p>AN EXACT JOURNAL OF THE SIEGE OF NAMUR: Giving a Particular ACCOUNT Of the ſeveral <hi>Sallies</hi> and <hi>Attacks,</hi> and other moſt remarkable <hi>Paſſages</hi> from the firſt <hi>Inveſting</hi> of the <hi>Place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TOGETHER WITH The ARTICLES of <hi>Capitulation,</hi> both for the Surrendring the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Caſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>I. Whitlock,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:98680:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98680:3"/>
            <head>AN EXACT JOURNAL OF THE SIEGE OF Namur, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>FOR the better underſtanding the Motions of both Armies, ſo ſoon as they took the Field; of the <hi>Confederates</hi> ſtriving to amuſe the Enemy; and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their main Deſign; and of the <hi>French,</hi> deluded by thoſe Amuſements, and endeavouring to defend themſelves from the feign'd Attempts of the <hi>Confede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ates,</hi> 'tis neceſſary that we ſhould make a Repetition of the Movements on both ſides from the beginning of the Campagne; ſince they all tended to a Siege; of which Poſterity, as well as the preſent Age, will be glad to have an Exact Account.</p>
            <p>The Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhal <hi>de Villeroy</hi> was no ſooner arriv'd in the <hi>French</hi> Army, but that he might win the Affection of ſo many great Officers, over whom he was to command, he told the chiefeſt among 'em, that he had in his Stables a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98680:4"/>Hundred Horſes, which they might make uſe of when they had occaſion: That he would alſo keep Three. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, where they would do him a kindneſs to come and Eat, and that his Purſe was ſtill at their Service. After theſe Complements, the <hi>French</hi> General having viſited all the Army that lay in different Quarters, from <hi>Furnes</hi> to the <hi>Meuſe,</hi> caus'd thoſe Troops that lay about <hi>Kièvraine,</hi> to paſs the River <hi>Haiſne,</hi> the 3d of <hi>June,</hi> in order to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp at <hi>Blaton,</hi> Two Leagues from <hi>Condè.</hi> The 6th, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Four in the Afternoon, he order'd the whole Army to march, and take up their Poſt in the Camp at <hi>Leuſe.</hi> The ſame Day alſo, M. <hi>de Bouflers</hi> encamp'd with his Army at <hi>Goſſeliers,</hi> upon the <hi>Pieton,</hi> Two Leagues from <hi>Charleroy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time, the King of <hi>England,</hi> who arriv'd at <hi>Gaunt,</hi> the 6th of <hi>June,</hi> departed the ſame day for the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my which lay at <hi>Aerſeel,</hi> near <hi>Thielt,</hi> under the Command of the Prince of <hi>Vaudemont,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Wirtembergh.</hi> The next day his Majeſty viſited all the Poſts round about the Camp.</p>
            <p>The Marſhal <hi>de Villeroy</hi> being inform'd of the King's Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival in the Army, upon the 8th, by Five in the Morning, Decamp'd from <hi>Leuſe,</hi> and marching all that Day and the next, upon the 10th encamp'd at <hi>Cordes</hi> between <hi>Tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay</hi> and <hi>Oudenard.</hi> The ſame day he viſited the Lines, between the <hi>Lys</hi> and the <hi>Scheld,</hi> and between <hi>Ypres</hi> and the <hi>Lys,</hi> and order'd the raiſing of ſome new Baſtions from <hi>Ypres</hi> to <hi>Commines,</hi> and to furniſh 'em ſufficiently with great Guns.</p>
            <p>Upon the 10th. the King took a review of the Horſe, and upon the 11th, detach'd away Twelve Squadrons, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Marqueſs <hi>de la Foret,</hi> Lieutenant General, who paſs'd the <hi>Lys</hi> at <hi>Machelen,</hi> over Three Bridges, with Orders to joyn the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who lay encamp'd with his Army at <hi>Ninove.</hi> The ſame day alſo the King decamp'd, and to the End he might draw nearer to the Lines, encamp'd at <hi>Rouſſelare,</hi> over againſt <hi>Commines</hi> and <hi>Ypres,</hi> and advanc'd the 13th to <hi>Bekelar,</hi> a League or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98680:4"/>from the Enemies Lines. Now in regard this Move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment threatned the very Center of 'em, as well as <hi>Menin, Ypres, la Kenoque, Furnes,</hi> the Canal <hi>d' Eauve</hi> and <hi>Boaſingue: Villeroy</hi> ſeem'd to be at a great puzzle, not knowing well what effectual Courſe to take for the Preſervation of ſo many Places at a time. Thereupon he forthwith iſſued out ſeveral Orders; he caus'd great Numbers of Men to march ſeveral ways, under ſeveral Commanders, and chang'd the Poſts of ſeveral. M. <hi>de Roſen,</hi> who lay at <hi>Eſchem,</hi> to defend the Line from <hi>Courtrai</hi> to the <hi>Scheld,</hi> paſs'd to <hi>Ypres</hi> to defend the whole on that ſide, M. <hi>de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trevel,</hi> was ſent to <hi>Eſchem,</hi> in the Place of M. <hi>de Roſen.</hi> M. <hi>de Capeſtan</hi> was appointed to command at <hi>Kenoke;</hi> the Count <hi>de la Motte,</hi> to command at <hi>Ypres,</hi> and M. <hi>de Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contal</hi> at <hi>Comines.</hi> M. <hi>de Caraman</hi> commanded to <hi>Ypres,</hi> and M. <hi>Davejan</hi> to <hi>Courtray,</hi> and M. <hi>de Montal</hi> lay next to <hi>Dunkirk.</hi> The Marſhal alſo order'd ſeveral Pieces of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non to be planted upon the Riſing Grounds of <hi>Hollebeck,</hi> where he had rais'd new Works, as having obſerv'd that part to be weaker than any of the reſt.</p>
            <p>During theſe Motions, the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who lay encamp'd at <hi>Ninove,</hi> departed from thence the 14th, paſs'd the <hi>Dendre,</hi> and encamp'd at St. <hi>Stephens.</hi> The 15th he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd at <hi>Ename</hi> upon the <hi>Scheldt,</hi> a League below <hi>Oudenarde;</hi> and the 17th encampt at <hi>Caſtre,</hi> within half a League of the Enemies new Line. On the other ſide, the Marſhal <hi>de Bouflers</hi> who lay with the Body of an Army at St. <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain,</hi> to obſerve the Electors Motions, being inform'd of theſe Movements, departed the 15th, and encamp'd near <hi>Tournai.</hi> The 16th he drew near the <hi>Scheld,</hi> and the 17th encamp'd under the Lines of <hi>Courtrai,</hi> where he receiv'd a Reinforcement of Horſe and Foot, that <hi>Villeroy</hi> ſent him.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time that the Elector encamp'd at <hi>Ninove,</hi> the Count of <hi>Athlone</hi> was detach'd from his Army, with Two and Twenty Squadrons of Horſe, and Nine of <hi>Dutch</hi> Dragoons, and ſome <hi>Bavarian</hi> Troops, to march toward <hi>Louvain,</hi> and joyn, if it were neceſſary, with the Troops
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98680:5"/>of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> and <hi>Liege,</hi> that lay quarter'd at <hi>Hologne,</hi> about a League from that City, and where they were joyn'd with the Brigadier <hi>Damprè,</hi> with Four Regiments of <hi>Dutch</hi> Horſe; and from whence they decamp'd the 18th, in order to march to <hi>Mehaigne.</hi> All which time, the Count <hi>de Harcourt</hi> lay with a Volant Camp of <hi>French</hi> Horſe in the <hi>Condros,</hi> to obſerve the Confederates on this ſide.</p>
            <p>Marſhal <hi>de Villeroy</hi> being inform'd, that the King of <hi>England</hi> drew near the Lines between <hi>Ypres</hi> and <hi>Warneton,</hi> decamp'd from <hi>Cordes,</hi> and march'd all Night of the 13th and 14th. The Foot being led by the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> and the Horſe by the Duke of <hi>Bourbon;</hi> and the whole Army encamp'd at <hi>Houthem</hi> in Two-Lines, the firſt all of Infantry, the Second all of Cavalry.</p>
            <p>Till the 19th, the <hi>French</hi> wrought hard to ſecure their Works rais'd all along the Lines; they alſo preſs'd forward the finiſhing of the New Works, and diſtributed Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition among the Soldiers. All the care of the <hi>French</hi> having been by theſe Motions, to retrench the more ſafely, and ſo to order it, that they might not be conſtrained to come to a Fight; a Proof ſufficient that the <hi>Confederates</hi> were Superior to 'em in Number.</p>
            <p>Upon the 17th, the King detach'd away the Duke of <hi>Wirtembergh,</hi> with 3000 Men, and ſome Artillery, with Orders to advance toward <hi>Kenoque,</hi> to the end he might draw the Enemy that way, and make 'em believe that there was a real Deſign upon that Fort: But before they could get thither, there was a Poſt that ſtood in their way, about half a League from the Fort, of which it behov'd 'em to make themſelves Maſters. This Poſt was defended by above 400 Dragoons, who were attacqu'd with ſuch an undaunted Bravery, as ſurpriz'd the Enemy themſelves. M. <hi>de la Motte,</hi> who commanded on that ſide, ſent a Reinforcement to his own, ſo that there was brisk Firing on both ſides: But at length the <hi>French</hi> were forc'd to give way, and the Aſſailants made themſelves Maſters both of the Poſt, and the Mote on that ſide: They alſo lodg'd themſelves there, and made a Battery of Two Pieces of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98680:5"/>Canon in the ſame Place. It was the common Opinion, that in this Action, the Duke of <hi>Wirtemberg</hi> loſt about Two Hundred, and the Enemy near Four Hundred Men.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the Count <hi>de la Motte</hi> caus'd another Battery to be rais'd in Oppoſition to that which the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates</hi> had erected, and they began to play one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with great Fury. The <hi>French</hi> alſo made all the haſte they could to entrench themſelves beyond the <hi>Yſer,</hi> caſting up the Earth before the River, becauſe the Moat which they poſſeſſed, lay lower than that which was oppoſite to it, the Ground being Marſhy. They were alſo Maſters of part of another Moat, which lay under the Canon of <hi>la Kenoque:</hi> And they ſhelter'd themſelves beſides, by means of a Parapet which they rais'd all the length of the Ground which look'd toward the <hi>Conſederates,</hi> and which they cut in two or Three Places, to render the Acceſs more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult.</p>
            <p>Upon the 20th in the Afternoon, the Duke of <hi>Wirtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> being ſtrengthned with ſome new Reinforcements, <hi>Villeroy</hi> who had notice of it, ſent away from the Left Wing of his Army, Eight Battalions, and a Brigade of Horſe, under the Marquis of <hi>Feuquieres,</hi> Lieutenant General. The Night of the 20th to the 21ſt, was ſpent in continual Skirmiſhes; and there was a Report ſpread Abroad, that <hi>la Kenoque</hi> was aſſayl'd in Military Forms: But that was almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, and it was ſufficiently apparent, that the Aſſaylants had no deſign to do it; but only to draw down all the ſtrength of the Enemy to that ſide of <hi>Flanders,</hi> by feigning the Seige of <hi>la Kenoque,</hi> and thereby cauſe the <hi>French</hi> to run at the wrong Deer. For it was a moſt difficult Task to paſs the <hi>Yſer,</hi> by reaſon of the Works which the <hi>French</hi> had caſt up; and there was no attacquing the Fort, without paſſing that River: And though the Confederates had paſs'd it, there lay beyond the broken Bridge, a great Quagmire, with a Road about Thirty Foot broad, wherein the <hi>French</hi> had made ſeveral Entrenchments one behind another. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, <hi>Montal</hi> commanded with his Volant Camp, from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98680:6"/>
               <hi>Dunkirk</hi> to <hi>Fintelle:</hi> His Forces ſtretching themſelves from <hi>Furnes</hi> to this Place, which is a Conſiderable Poſt, well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd with Men, becauſe that they who would paſs the <hi>Yſer</hi> muſt take it before they can come at <hi>Furnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While theſe things were thus Acting on this ſide, the Elector of <hi>Bevaria</hi> lay not Idle. Upon the 17th of <hi>June</hi> the Horſe and Foot had orders to prepare Facines or Faggots to be lay'd before the Regiments. The 19th the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector riding with between three and four thouſand Horſe to View the Ground about the <hi>Lines,</hi> found that the <hi>French</hi> had poſted themſelves at the Mill of <hi>Belleghem,</hi> which is not above half a Quarter of a League from Fort <hi>de Clar,</hi> and the Lines. In this Place were poſted five hundred Foot, and eight or ten Squardrons. Therefore M. General <hi>Fagel</hi> was ſent away with ſome Troops to make himſelf Maſter of the Poſt. The Onſet was Rude and Obſtinate, for they charg'd and return'd to the Charge ſeveral times. But the <hi>French</hi> were conſtrain'd to give way, and retreated into their Lines the beſt they could, and in great diſorder, being cloſely purſu'd by the Confederates. The <hi>Mill</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus taken, the Victors entrench'd themſelves upon the Place, and maintain'd their ground.</p>
            <p>By this time ſome part of <hi>June</hi> being ſpent in all theſe Attacks, and having ſufficiently fatigu'd and remov'd the Enemy at a diſtance from the Place where the Attaque was really deſign'd, private Orders were given to the <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burghers,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Athlone,</hi> to the Army of the Elector of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia</hi> and the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Forces, to ſet forward in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to put in Execution the Deſign which had been lay'd ſome time before. For all this while the Confederates, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> order to what they cheifly propos'd to themſelves, had made great Preparations at <hi>Leige</hi> of Great Guns, Ammunition and Proviſion, Pickaxes, Spades, Shovels and other Uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſils for Seiges, which were conveigh'd by Water down the River <hi>Meuſe.</hi> They had got together a great Body of Men compos'd of the Troops of <hi>Munſter, Cologn, Leige, Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburghers</hi> and others, who were advanc'd as far as <hi>Falaiſe,</hi> upon the <hi>Mehaigne.</hi> Theſe were all order'd to march
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98680:6"/>directly for <hi>Namur;</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Athlone</hi> decamp'd from <hi>Bethlem</hi>'s, tending his march to the ſame Place. He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp'd at <hi>Roesbeck</hi> the 22d where he made a Halt one day; then marching three days together, and croſſing the Famous Plain of <hi>Fleurus,</hi> he encamp'd the 29th at <hi>Mellé,</hi> within an hour and a half's march of <hi>Charleroi</hi> While the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> got before and advanc'd ſtill nearer to the <hi>Samber:</hi> And upon the 2d of <hi>July,</hi> he croſs'd the <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> and inveſted <hi>Namur</hi> on that ſide next <hi>Condros.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> decamp'd from <hi>Caſtre,</hi> about the 28th at night, and came the next morning to St. <hi>Lievens Hauten,</hi> and the 30th encamp'd at <hi>Ninove.</hi> The 1ſt of <hi>July</hi> he came to <hi>Hall,</hi> and the next day to <hi>Maſy,</hi> within two leagues of <hi>Namur.</hi> The 3d he made his Approaches nearer to the City, croſs'd the <hi>Samber,</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted his Men and took up his Head Quarters in the <hi>Abby de Maloigne.</hi> The Baron of <hi>Heiden,</hi> General of the <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burghers,</hi> who had paſs'd the <hi>Samber</hi> below <hi>Charleroi,</hi> took his Poſt next to <hi>Morlaigne,</hi> and ſent a Detachment over the <hi>Meuſe</hi> on that ſide next to <hi>Condros.</hi> While the Earl of <hi>Athlone</hi> poſted himſelf on this ſide the <hi>Meuſe</hi> with his Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: And thus <hi>Namur,</hi> upon the 3d of <hi>June,</hi> was inveſted on every ſide.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain</hi> upon the 27th of <hi>June</hi> ſent away the heavy Baggage, the Suttlers and the Artillery from the Camp at <hi>Bekelaer:</hi> And the 28th by five a clock in the morning the whole Army decamp'd in two Colums, and marching on both ſides of the Road with the Artillery encamp'd at <hi>Rouſſelaer.</hi> In the mean time the Duke of <hi>Wirtemberg</hi> having demoliſh'd the Poſt which he had made himſelf Maſter off, retreated to <hi>Dixmude</hi> with the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy under his command.</p>
            <p>The 29th his Majeſty having left the Army to the Conduct of the Prince of <hi>Vaudemont,</hi> departed with a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment of Granadiers and the Guards of his Body, and took the Road of <hi>Vilvorde.</hi> However ten thouſand Men of that Army had orders to march to <hi>Bruſſels</hi> through <hi>Deinſe, Gaure,</hi> and <hi>Aloſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98680:7"/>
            <p>His Majeſty lay the 30th at <hi>Grimbery,</hi> and the 1ſt of <hi>July</hi> at the Abby of <hi>Parc</hi> near <hi>Lovain.</hi> The 2d he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived near <hi>Namur</hi> about a eleven a clock in the forenoon, and took up his Head Quarters at <hi>Coutoix le Chaſteau.</hi> He held a Council of War that Evening, and the next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Army drew nearer the City. The 3d his Majeſty took up his Quarters at <hi>Flawen,</hi> on this ſide the <hi>Samber.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Villeroy</hi> obſerving theſe unexpected Movements, ſent away ſeveral Detachments to joyn <hi>Bouflers.</hi> But the Prince of <hi>Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demont</hi> who watches the <hi>French</hi> General, ſent away as many Detachments from his Army, as the Marſhal detach'd from his, and Encampt at <hi>Gramme</hi> near <hi>Deinſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 4th in the Evening the Beſeigers began to fall brisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to work in drawing and making their Lines of Circum-Vallation, and Contra-Vallation; but notwithſtanding all their diligence they could not prevent <hi>Bouflers</hi> from getting into the Town with ſeveral Regiments of Dragoons, and M. <hi>Meg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igni</hi> the Chiefeſt Engineer in <hi>France,</hi> next to M. <hi>Vauban.</hi> So that there was then ſaid to be in the Town and Cittadel, beſides thoſe Seven Regiments, one and twenty Battalions, a Regiment of Cavalry, ſeveral Great Officers, a Company of Frank Volunteers, a Company of Canoneers, another of Miners, a Brigade of Engineers, and Ammunition and Proviſions for ſix Months. By the 12th the Lines being finiſh'd, and ſome Batteries to cover the Workmen and Pioneers, the ſame evening the Trenches were open'd in three ſeveral Places; and the Beſeigers play'd from one Battery while the Workmen labour'd without ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to bring the reſt to perfection: During which time the Beſeiged made three Sallies, but in every one had no Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, being ſtill repuls'd with loſs: Tho' Mr. General <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> was wounded in one of 'em, and the Baron of <hi>Plettem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi>'s Nephew, and a very good Officer, Slain with a Cannon Bullet.</p>
            <p>On the 8th of <hi>July</hi> N. S. Twenty Battalions of Foot, of which Thirteen were <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch,</hi> being ſent from the Prince of <hi>Vaudemont</hi>'s Army joyn'd the Beſeigers, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of the Count of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> Lieutenant
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98680:7"/>General, and M. General <hi>Ramſey;</hi> and upon the 10th, Four <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and Two Battalions of <hi>Dutch,</hi> under the lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord <hi>Cutts,</hi> arriv'd in the Camp; ſo that the Beſiegers were then no leſs 90 Battalions of Infantry. The Artillery alſo conſiſted of 120 Great Guns, and 60 Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars.</p>
            <p>Upon the 12th of <hi>July,</hi> Major General <hi>Saliſh</hi> relieved the Trenches; the next day, Major General <hi>Lindeboome,</hi> and upon the 14th, Major General <hi>Henkelem.</hi> During which time, the Beſiegers Works and Approaches being carried on within Piſtol-ſhot of the Enemies Out-works upon the Hill near <hi>Bruſſels</hi> Gate, his Majeſty reſolv'd to ſtorm thoſe Works. To which purpoſe, all things being in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, the Attack was begun on <hi>Monday</hi> the 15th, about Six a Clock in the Afternoon, upon the Right Hand, by Five Battalions of the Foot-Guards, commanded by Major General <hi>Ramſey,</hi> ſeconded by Nine Battalions more of <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch:</hi> Upon the Left, Eight <hi>Dutch,</hi> and other Regiments under the Command of Major General <hi>Saliſh,</hi> were order'd to undertake the Aſſault. This Attack was performed with a more than ordinary Courage, and a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs anſwerable. For after a very ſharp and obſtinate Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, that held near upon Two Hours, the Beſieged were beaten out of their Forts upon the Hill, and a Great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchment that leads to the Town, of which the Victors poſſeſſed themſelves, being the moſt conſiderable Outworks which the Beſiegers had on this ſide.</p>
            <p>In this Attack, the Beſiegers had in all about 300 Men ſlain out-right, and 400 Wounded. Of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Guards, Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Robinſon,</hi> Five Lieutenants, and Two Enſigns were ſlain; Colonel <hi>Matthews,</hi> and ſeveral others were wounded. Of the <hi>French</hi> ſide; M. <hi>Moulevier,</hi> and M. <hi>de Vitry</hi> who acted as Brigadiers, and the Count of <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein,</hi> Son in Law to the Duke of <hi>Chevreuſe,</hi> with about 50 Commanders more of Note kill'd, beſides Inferior Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and about 1600 Men Kill'd and Wounded,</p>
            <p>The ſame day, about Two Hours before this deſperate Attack, the Beſieged made a Sally upon the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98680:8"/>Quarter, but after a ſharp Conflict, were beaten back, and purſu'd to the very Gates of the Fort near the <hi>Meuſe.</hi> The Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies loſs could not chooſe but be very conſiderable, on the other ſide the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> loſt a Collonel, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officers kill'd, and had about a Hundred Men kill'd and wounded.</p>
            <p>On the <hi>Tueſday</hi> Night following, Major General <hi>Heuke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> reliev'd the Trenches; the next Night, Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Saliſh,</hi> and on <hi>Thurſday</hi> Night, Major General <hi>Ramſey.</hi> And at the ſame time, they had ſeveral Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries playing againſt the detach'd Baſtions, that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Bruſſels</hi> and St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> Gate, toward which they were making their Approaches with all the ſpeed they could.</p>
            <p>While things were thus hotly diſputed between the Beſiegers and the Beſieged at <hi>Namur,</hi> Marſhal <hi>de Villeroy</hi> well underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Army under the Command of the Prince of <hi>Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demont</hi> was very much weaken'd by the ſending of ſeveral Detachments to the Siege and other Places, thought he bad now an Opportunity to do a conſiderable piece of Service for his Maſter, by cutting off ſo conſiderable a part of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Forces: To which purpoſe he drain'd all the <hi>French</hi> Garriſons round about, and having by that means drawn together a Force that was almoſt treble in Number to the Prince of <hi>Vaudemont,</hi> he ſet forward with a full Reſolution to fall upon him in his Trenches, in Front, Flank and Rear; confident he had him in ſuch a Snare, that 'twas im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible a Man ſhould eſcape him.</p>
            <p>'Twas upon the 10th of <hi>July</hi> therefore, that the <hi>French</hi> Army under <hi>Villeroy</hi> decamp'd from <hi>Pont Eſcanaffe,</hi> and quitted their Lines to attack the Prince, who lay near <hi>Deinſe.</hi> Now in regard that the Confederates were ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp'd, that the Enemy would have had 'em in Flank, the Prince thought it convenient to alter the Array of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and to poſt his Right Wing beyond <hi>Aerſeele,</hi> whereas it was poſted at <hi>Dendergem;</hi> and the Left Wing he poſted all along the <hi>Lys,</hi> a little above <hi>Gramme,</hi> whereas before it was poſted at <hi>Zeveren,</hi> near <hi>Deinſe.</hi> About Eight a Clock
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98680:8"/>in the Evening, ſome Squadrons of the Enemies, advanced as far as <hi>Dendergem,</hi> and began to charge the Prince's Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd Guards, who retreated between <hi>Dendergem,</hi> and the Front of the Army, according to the Orders they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <p>The Night following, the Prince order'd a Line to be caſt up, to cover his Left Wing and Main Body, and order'd ſeveral Pieces of Canon to be planted in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Avenues to the Camp. The 14th, between Seven and Eight in the Morning, it was eaſily perceiv'd, that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies Army began to reach <hi>Denderghem,</hi> making a ſhew as if they intended to ſide off to the Princes Left Wing. In the mean time the Right Wing was ſurrounded with a Line, as the Left and the Main Body had been environ'd before: But the Enemy made a Halt near <hi>Denderghem,</hi> till about Noon, when their whole Army fil'd along the High-way of <hi>Thielt,</hi> and came to poſt themſelves within Canon ſhot of the Prince's Right Wing: And then it was, that the Prince expected a General Aſſault. But they durſt not venture to attacque him, ſeeing him ſo well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench'd, and in ſo very good Order to receive them, the Great Guns being extreamly well dispos'd for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Prince having Advice, that the Count of <hi>Montal</hi> was filing along his Right Wing, with a great Body of Horſe and Foot, in order to charge 'em in the Rear, and the Marſhal to attacque him in the Front, for that their Forces were much more numerous than His, the Prince immediately caus'd all the Baggage to paſs the <hi>Scheld</hi> at <hi>Deinſe,</hi> from thence to be Convoy'd to <hi>Gaunt,</hi> which was done. Afterwards, he drew off his Artillery from the Batteries, and order'd them to take the ſame Road; as alſo the Ammunition Waggons, and the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, in ſeveral little Bodies.</p>
            <p>And the better to hinder the Enemy from perceiving his Retreat, the Prince order'd <hi>M. d' Overkirk</hi> to face the Enemy, with all the Horſe and Dragoons of the Right
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98680:9"/>Wing, and for that purpoſe to range himſelf in Battel Array, from <hi>Aerſeel</hi> to <hi>Vink,</hi> which was done; and after the Artillery, Baggage, Ammunition-Waggons and Foot were got far enough before, M. <hi>de Overkirk</hi> follow'd with the Cavalry and Dragoons, as the Prince had order'd him.</p>
            <p>Thus was the Enemy amus'd, notwithſtanding they lay ſo very near, and that the Prince did not begin to march till about Five or Six of the Clock in the Afternoon, and conſequently in open Day-light. And this March was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd in ſo good Order and with ſo much Speed, that the Enemy durſt not attack the <hi>Conſederates.</hi> Nor had they loſt one Man, but for a Stratagem which the <hi>French</hi> us'd, which was by making uſe of Green Colours, to intermix with ſome of the Rear guard, and to fall upon Two Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talions, and ſome Granadeers, before they could get in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Lane through which they were to paſs. But the Granadeers, and another Battalion making a Halt, the Enemy was ſoon repulſed: However this Stratagem coſt the <hi>Confederates</hi> 200 Men. The Marſhal enrag'd that ſuch an Opportunity had ſlipt out of his Hands, Burnt and Plunder'd the Village of <hi>Wootergen,</hi> where the Prince had his Head Quarters.</p>
            <p>When his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> was inform'd that the Army and the Prince were ſafe, and what a Brave and Maſterlike Retreat he had made, he ſent the Prince the enſuing Letter.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98680:9"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Couſin,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> may well imagin how uneaſie I was upon the Receipt of your laſt Letter, dated Yeſterday Noon, which came to me this Morning by break of Day; and how great a Joy your other Letter was to me, Dated from <hi>Marykerk,</hi> near <hi>Gaunt,</hi> this Day at Three of the Clock in the Morning, finding that you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood ſo well with ſo much prudence, and ſo gloriouſly to diſingage your ſelf from ſo imminent a Danger. I am much oblig'd to you for it; for in this Retreat you have given greater Marks of a general accompliſhment in the Art of War, than if you had won a Battel. I abſolutely approve your Conduct upon this occaſion, and I hope it will caution the Enemy from attempting any more of the ſame Nature. In the mean time, I impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently expect to hear which way they will bend their March, now they have miſs'd their Blow. I remain always, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From the Camp before <hi>Namur,</hi> 
                        <date>the 15th, at Nine a Clock in the Evening.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Sign'd, <hi>WILLIAM REX.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:98680:10"/>
            <p>But to return to the Siege; after the Attack on <hi>Monday</hi> was over, a Letter was intercepted from M. <hi>Bouflers</hi> to the King of <hi>France,</hi> wherein, after the Marſhal had given him a Relation of the particulars of the Attack, he very much lamented, that it had coſt his Majeſty above a Thouſand Men, among which he reckon'd the Counts of <hi>Maulevrier</hi> and <hi>Morſtein,</hi> the Marquis of <hi>Monbron,</hi> the Governor of <hi>Cambray</hi>'s Son, Colonel of the Dauphin's Regiment, Two other Colonels, 16 Captains, and ſeveral good Officers and Perſons of Note. It was a Woman who undertook to carry the Letter to <hi>Dinant,</hi> from thence to be ſent to the Court; but inſtead of the Recompence which M. <hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flers</hi> put her in hopes of receiving for her pains, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers hang'd her up upon a Gibbet, that ſhe might ſerve for an Example to others, who ſhould undertake ſuch kind of Meſſages.</p>
            <p>On the 18th of <hi>July,</hi> Orders were given out for Major General <hi>Ramſey,</hi> with Five Battalions of Guards, to Storm an Old Tower that ſtands below a certain Place call'd <hi>la Bouge,</hi> and the Enemies Works deſcending toward the Counterſcarp; the order of which Attack was thus. The Firſt Battalion of the Firſt Regiment of Guards, a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion of <hi>Coldſtreamers</hi> Regiment of Guards, and a Battalion of <hi>Scotch</hi> Guards, were order'd for the Attack upon the Right Hand, toward the bottom. The Second Battalion of the firſt Regiment of Guards, was appointed for the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack on the Left Hand, by the Old Tower. At the Head of theſe Attacks, march'd a Hundred and Twenty Fuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers, who carried Faſcines before them; and the ſame number of Granadiers, follow'd by a Hundred Pioneers with Spades, Shovels and Gabions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> On the Right of the Body which advanced on the Right Hand, march'd a Hundred Granadiers, carrying Faſcines before them, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd by Fifty Pioneers; and the ſame Number of Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers was on the Right of the Body on the Left Hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Two Attacks.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98680:10"/>
            <p>Half an Hour after Six a Clock in the Afternoon, the Signal was given, at what time the Battalions before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd march'd forward in the appointed Order, with that undaunted Courage and Bravery, which is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, never taking any notice of the Enemies Firing, which was very thick and furious: For the Fuſeliers that were in the Front, advanc'd with their Faſcines to the very Paliſado's, where when they had laid 'em down, they fell a Firing upon the Enemy, while the Granadiers ply'd the Tower and Works, the Battalions in the mean time march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſe after 'em, with their Muskets ſhoulder'd, till they came ſo very near, that they preſented over the Paliſados, driving the Defendants from thence, and purſuing them through a wide Place of Arms, to the bottom of the Work.</p>
            <p>But the Enemy firing a-freſh from the Counterſcarp, and a Redoubt that lay on the other ſide of a Hollow way, upon the Aſſailant's Flank, the Lord <hi>Cuts</hi> immediately haſten'd to ſecond thoſe that were engag'd, with Three Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talions of <hi>Titcomb, Stanley</hi> and <hi>Collingwood;</hi> with the Firſt of which, he flew to the loweſt Paliſados, and together with the Guards, a Second time beat back the Enemy, ſome into the Water, others where they could beſt ſhift for themſelves.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time Brigadier <hi>Fitzpatrick,</hi> with the Lord <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s, his own Regiment of Fuſeliers, <hi>Ingolsby, Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſon, Lowder</hi> and <hi>Maitland,</hi> ſet forward toward the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks, with the Two Firſt to relieve the <hi>Dutch</hi> Guards, and thoſe that were with the Lord <hi>Cutts,</hi> at the loweſt Paliſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do's; the reſt were drawn up by the Tower, to give aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as occaſion requir'd; only <hi>Lowders</hi> Regiment was poſted on the other ſide of the Hollow way, to prevent Flanking and Surprize. In the mean time, Major General <hi>Ramſey</hi> commanded the Pike-men to carry Faſcines, and raiſe a work ſufficient to withſtand a Musket Shot; and when he had poſted in that Place, the Regiments of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>golsby, Sanderſon, Lowder</hi> and <hi>Maitland,</hi> he drew off the reſt by break of Day, to the Firſt Parade. The Fury
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98680:11"/>and Heat of this Action laſted about Two Hours, in which time the Beſiegers poſſeſſed themſelves of the Enemies Works, notwithſtanding they were defended by ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Numbers of Reſolute Men. In this Bloody Action, the Aſſailants both Officers and Soldiers, ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd themſelves to that degree, that 'twas no wonder that they who did more than Men could be thought to do, ſhould be ſuperior and victorious over thoſe who did no more than only what Men could do.</p>
            <p>The chief Officers Slain and Wounded, were Colonel <hi>Robinſon</hi> Kill'd, Lieutenant Colonel <hi>How,</hi> and Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Davis</hi> Wounded, of the Firſt Regiment of Guards. In the <hi>Coldſtream</hi> Guards, Colonel <hi>Matthews,</hi> Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Edgeworth,</hi> and Leiutenant Colonel <hi>Jones</hi> Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Pierce</hi> and <hi>Moriſon,</hi> Lieutenant Collonels taken Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Guards, Lieutenant Colonel <hi>John Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton</hi> wounded. Of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Guards, <hi>Goudaker</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute,</hi> Lieutenant Colonels, and Major <hi>Hetzler</hi> wounded. Of the Royal Regiment, Major <hi>Mac Ilvain</hi> Slain, and the Lord <hi>George Hamilton</hi> Wounded. Of Colonel <hi>Ingolsby</hi>'s Regiment, Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Sabin</hi> Wounded, beſides ſeveral Captains, Lieutenants and Enſigns, and others Kill'd and Wounded; and the whole Loſs of Private Soldiers, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Account given in by the ſeveral Colonels, was 308 Slain, and 604 Wounded. And as for the Enemy, they had no leſs than 1600 Kill'd and Wounded, by the Information of the Deſerters.</p>
            <p>In this Interim, <hi>Villeroy</hi> had laid a Deſign to have ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd <hi>Nieuport,</hi> by means of a Correſpondence which he held with a Perſon who had undertaken to deliver the Sluces into his Hands. But the Prince of <hi>Vaudemont</hi> having an inkling of it, ſent immediate Orders to Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> (whom he had detach'd ſome Days before toward <hi>Bruges,</hi> with Twelve Battalions) to march with all ſpeed toward the Canal, and diſpute the Paſſage with the Enemy, which he did the next Night. The <hi>French</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing of this, continu'd their March toward the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, but ſeeing Twelve Battalions poſted on the other ſide,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98680:11"/>they were ſo aſtoniſhed, that they deſiſted from their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and retreated faſter than they came, fearing to be ſwallow'd up by the Waters of the Sluces which the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor had open'd upon their Approach. And as for the Traytor, finding himſelf diſappointed, he made his Eſcape to <hi>Furnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 25th at Night, the Beſiegers poſted themſelves at the Foot of the Redoubt of <hi>Pallart,</hi> and about Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, ſet their Miners to work: Which enforc'd the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that defended it, to ſurrender at diſcretion by break of Day, being in all Six and Fifty Men, among whom were a Captain, an Engineer, Two Lieutenants, and an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
            <p>Upon the 27th of <hi>July</hi> in the Morning, his Majeſty ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving reſolv'd that an Attack ſhould be made upon the Firſt Counterſcarp of the Town, came into the Trenches him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and after he had given ample and requiſite Orders, more particularly, that all the Batteries as well of the Great Guns as Mortars, ſhould play without intermiſſion upon the Faces of the Baſtion, before St. <hi>Nicholas</hi>'s Gate, and the front of the Counterguard that lay upon the Left Hand of the Ravelin near the <hi>Meuſe,</hi> return'd to his Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. In the Afternoon, he went again into the Trenches, and about Five a Clock in the Afternoon, the Attack be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> march'd from the Head of the Trenches on the Right Hand, and advanc'd to the firſt Counterſcarp that covers the Sluces. All the while the Enemy fir'd thick and furiouſly, and ſprang Three or Four ſmall Mines fill'd with Bombs upon the Glacis; nevertheleſs the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailants made themſelves Maſters of the Counterſcarp, and while they drave the Enemy from their Defences, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers made a Lodgment behind 'em upon the Glacis of the Counterſcarp before mention'd.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time the <hi>Dutch</hi> march'd upon the Left Hand, and advancing along the <hi>Meuſe,</hi> fell upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who defended the Firſt and Second Counterſcarp in Flank, and in leſs than a Quarter of an Hour drove the Beſieged out of the firſt Counterſcarp, from one end to the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98680:12"/>other. Which done, the Aſſailants preſently began to lodge themſelves with Wool-ſacks, Gabions and Faſcines, ſome of which unfortunately taking Fire, burnt a part of the Lodgment, made by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to ſecure their Left againſt the Counterguard of St. <hi>Rocque</hi>'s Baſtion. However the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> defenceleſs as they were, maintain'd their Ground, and kept the Enemy that were poſted within the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terguard in play, till they had made a new Lodgment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Firſt, which was at length put out. In the mean time the <hi>Dutch</hi> perceiving that the Enemies firing from the Counterguard, very much gall'd the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> mounted the Breach of the Counterſcarp next the <hi>Meuſe,</hi> plying the and Enemy with their Granado's, lodg'd themſelves upon the Breach of the Counterſcarp, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had done on the Counterſcarp it ſelf; by which means, they kept all the firſt Counterſcarp, from the <hi>Meuſe</hi> to the Inundation. The Enemy all this while kept firing continually with Five or Six Pieces of Canon, ſeveral of the Bullets of which flew near the Place where the King ſtood; and one of 'em kill'd Mr. <hi>Godfrey,</hi> and took off the Arm of Lieutenant Collonel <hi>d' Eck.</hi> Of the Beſiegers, between Three and Four Hundred Men were Kill'd and Wounded in this Action. Nor could the Enemies Loſs but be conſiderable, in regard that few of their Men who were poſted in the firſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſcarp, eſcap'd with their Lives; as alſo, for that the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailants Canon and Bombs, and the ſmall ſhot of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry did great Execution.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time, the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> attack'd, and made himſelf Maſter of an Advanc'd Poſt of the Enemies, between the <hi>Sambre</hi> and the Caſtle-Hill, wherein were lodg'd about Four Hundred Men, beſides a Detachment to guard the Abby of <hi>Salſine,</hi> and another Houſe that ſtood near it, Places both very proper for laying a Bridge over the <hi>Sambre,</hi> and to facilitate the Attack of the Caſtle. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this Action, the Beſieged Sally'd out of the Caſtle, both Horſe and Dragoons, to ſecond their Men, but upon the Electors ſending ſome Squadrons againſt 'em, they preſently retreated.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98680:12"/>
            <p>After theſe Two Attacks were over, his Majeſty order'd the Ditch of the Town to be drain'd; to which purpoſe, the Dam that kept in the Water, was undermin'd and blown up.</p>
            <p>Upon the 29th of <hi>July,</hi> it was reſolved that the Electors Men, ſhould the next Morning early, attack the Enemies Lines, and Retrenchments that ſecur'd all their New Works before the Caſtle, between the <hi>Sambre</hi> and the <hi>Meuſe:</hi> And the Forces appointed for this piece of Service, conſiſting of <hi>Bavarians, Brandenburghers,</hi> and other Foreign Troops, were order'd to move ſoon after it was dark, and during the Obſcurity of the Night, to advance ſo near the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Trenches as poſſibly they could, without being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd.</p>
            <p>Upon the 30th, as ſoon as Day was broke, the Signals being given, the Aſſaylants fell on in Three ſeveral Places. The Aſſent of the Hill proved ſomewhat difficult, beſides that the Enemy had Eight or Nine Great Guns, conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently planted at ſome diſtance without their Works, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional to thoſe mounted upon their Fortification. But notwithſtanding all this, the Beſieged were ſoon driven from their Lines, and that with ſo little Loſs on the Aſſailants ſide, that had they ſtop'd according to their Orders, there would have hardly been Twenty loſt. But the Granadiers in heat of Courage, purſuing the Fugitive Enemy, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd ſo far, that they drove 'em from the Counterſcarp of ſome of their ſtrongeſt and moſt regular Works; but not being provided to lodge themſelves, they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to retire to the Ground where they were firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to poſt themſelves, which was a good way within thoſe Lines, which were by the Enemy thought ſo ſtrong, as well by reaſon of their Scituation, as of the New Works which they had added ſince the Siege, that the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of 'em would have coſt much dearer than they did. This Action coſt the Beſiegers about a Hundred Men Slain, and a Hundred and Fifty Wounded. The <hi>French</hi> ſent out of the Caſtle both Horſe and Dragoons to ſecond their Men, but upon the marching of a Detachment no leſs nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98680:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98680:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:98680:14"/>againſt them, they preſently retreated, without making the leaſt Attempt.</p>
            <p>Upon the Firſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> his Majeſty caus'd an Onſet to be given to the Counterſcarp, before the Half Moon, and the Demi-Baſtion, on the Left Hand near the <hi>Meuſe.</hi> This Attack was begun about Seven a Clock in the Morning, by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Guards, under the command of the Lord <hi>Cutts</hi> upon the Right Hand, and on the Left by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> led by Brigadier <hi>Dedem;</hi> who notwithſtandig the continual Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Enemy, before Ten a Clock had lodg'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on the Right Hand, and ſecur'd their Lodgement. The <hi>Dutch</hi> alſo not being able to maintain the Work it ſelf, lodg'd themſelves upon the point of the Demi-baſtion: And this Action coſt the Beſiegers about Four Hundred Men Kill'd and Wounded, part <hi>Engliſh</hi> and part <hi>Dutch.</hi> In this, as in all the reſt of the Onſets made in the time of this Siege, the Soldiers behav'd themſelves with that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Courage and Bravery, that they carried all before them, and the Oldeſt and moſt experienc'd Officers declar'd that they never ſaw ſuch vigorous Storming of Ramparts and Bulwarks before.</p>
            <p>And now the Beſiegers being lodg'd upon the Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcarp, were preparing for a general Aſſault upon the Town; when upon the Third of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> about Two in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, the Enemy hung out a white Flag, and deſired a Parley; which being granted, Hoſtages were exchang'd, Colonel <hi>William Seymor,</hi> and Major <hi>Storek</hi> for the Beſiegers, and Count <hi>Nogent,</hi> and a <hi>French</hi> Major for the Beſieged. Upon which a Treaty enſu'd, and the Town was ſurrender'd upon a Capitulation that contain'd theſe following Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="articles">
               <body>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98680:14"/>
                  <head>Articles of Capitulation, demanded by the <hi>French,</hi> for the Surrendring of the Town of <hi>Namur.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>I.</hi> THE Exerciſe of the Roman Catholick Religion ſhall be preſerved in the Town, and no other permitted.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>II.</hi> All the Priviledges of the Inhabitants ſhall be preſerved, and their Goods that are Confiſcated, reſtored.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>III.</hi> All the Inhabitants, <hi>French</hi> and others, may ſtay in the Town, or remove in Three Months, with their Families and Effects.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>IV.</hi> None of the Burghers, or others, ſhall be troubled for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſerved the <hi>French</hi> King, and they, as well as all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerters, ſhall be Pardoned.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted, except what relates to the Deſerters.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>V.</hi> The Horſes taken during the War, and bought by the Burghers or others, ſhall not be taken from them.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>VI.</hi> The Sick and Wounded ſhall be Tranſported to <hi>Dinant,</hi> with the Perſons appointed to take care of them; and Boats and ſufficient Carriages ſhall be provided for them by the Allies, (they paying for the ſame) with the neceſſary Convoy and Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, within Six Days after Signing this Capitulation.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Beſieged may provide Boats for their Sick and Wounded, and ſhall have Paſports to ſend for what Boats and Boat-men they want from</hi> Dinant, <hi>and may make uſe of what Boats there are at</hi> Namur, <hi>provided they ſend them forthwith back again.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>VII.</hi> Such of the Sick and Wounded as are not in a condition to remove, may continue at <hi>Namur,</hi> and when they are well, ſhall be furniſhed with Carriages and Paſports to carry them to <hi>Dinant.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98680:15"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>VIII.</hi> Six Days ſhall be Granted to the Gariſon of the Town to retire into the Caſtle with their Families and Effects, during which time, no Hoſtility ſhall be committed by either Party, on the ſide of the Town or the Caſtle; and to prevent all diſorder, the Troops of the <hi>Allies</hi> ſhall only poſſeſs themſelves of the Gate of the firſt Encloſure of the Attack, and none of them ſhall enter into the Town, until the Gariſon is entirely retired into the Caſtle, and the Second Gate of the Second Attack, ſhall during the ſaid time, be guarded by the Gariſon.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>There are Granted to the Beſieged, Two Days only, to begin from the 4th at Noon, and they ſhall forthwith give up the Poſts at the Entrance of the Iron Gate. The Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged may place a Guard jointly with the Allies, at the Gate of the Old Encloſure, to prevent Diſorders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>IX.</hi> The Gariſons in the Redoubts of St. <hi>Fiacre, Eſpiney,</hi> and St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> may enter into the Town, and thence retire into the Caſtle.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>X.</hi> All Perſons put by the <hi>French</hi> King into any Places of Judicature, or others, ſhall continue to enjoy the ſame.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>XI.</hi> No Officers Sick or Wounded, or others, ſhall be ſtopt on accompt of Debt, or on any other Pretence, but Security ſhall be given to ſuch as can but make out their Debts, for Payment of the ſame.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>XII.</hi> All Contracts and Agreements made between the <hi>French</hi> and the Burghers, and with the Magiſtrates ſhall be faithfully performed.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted, provided the ſame be not prejudicial to his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Majeſty.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>XIII.</hi> The Horſes and Equipages of the Officers and Gariſon in the Town, ſhall be Conducted with a Convoy to <hi>Dinant,</hi> and they may not be ſtop'd or ſearched, on any Pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, and no prejudice done to the ſaid Equipages, or thoſe that conduct them.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rejected.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98680:15"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>XIV.</hi> The Priſoners taken during the Siege, ſhall be releas'd on both ſides.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>XV.</hi> All the Hoſtages may be conducted with a Convoy to <hi>Dinant.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>XVI.</hi> There ſhall be given up the Town, which is between the <hi>Sambre,</hi> and the Attack of St. <hi>Nicholas</hi>'s Gate, as alſo the Iron Gate, and the Two Towers which are at the end of the Gate of the <hi>Meuſe,</hi> towards the <hi>Condros,</hi> except Gate <hi>Lewis,</hi> which is to remain in the Hands of the Beſieged.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Granted.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>XVII.</hi> The Hoſtages given on both ſides for the due Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of theſe Articles, ſhall be reciprocally reſtored, after the full performance thereof.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Mines and the Magazines ſhall be diſcovered by the Beſieged to thoſe that ſhall be appointed for that Purpoſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Beſieged ſhall commit no Diſorder, nor inſult over the Inhabitants in quitting the Town.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Theſe Articles were Signed the 4th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and Count <hi>Guiſcard,</hi> Governor of Namur.</p>
                  </argument>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>No ſooner had the Confederates made themſelves Maſters of the Town of <hi>Namur,</hi> which they had bravely and fairly won in a manner by Inches, but the unhappy Tidings ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd, that <hi>Dixmude</hi> and <hi>Deinſe</hi> were both ſhamefully deliver'd up to the <hi>French,</hi> and the Garriſons made Priſoners of War; the one by the Treachery of Major General <hi>Ellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh,</hi> the other by the perfidiouſneſs of Colonel <hi>Ofarrel. Ellenbergh</hi> after he had done his buſineſs, retir'd to <hi>Paris,</hi> to receive the Rewards of his Villany; and <hi>Ofarrel</hi> ſhelter'd himſelf in <hi>Cambray.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:98680:16"/>
            <p>Upon the 12th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> at Night, the Beſiegers broke Ground, in order to make their Approaches to the Caſtle, and carrying on their Trenches about 150 Paces before <hi>Cohorn</hi> Fort, toward the <hi>Sambre,</hi> made a very good Lodgment. The 13th they advanc'd their Trenches about 200 Paces farther; and that Afternoon one of the Beſiegers Bombs fell into one of the Enemies Magazines, wherein lay about 500 Granados, and ſome Powder, which blew up, and did them conſiderable Damage. The 14th, the Beſiegers continu'd their Works with good Succeſs. The Night following, the Enemy made a Sally upon Six Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the Beſiegers, commanded by Colonel <hi>Seymour,</hi> who were poſted near the Paliſados of the <hi>French,</hi> to ſecure the Pioneers that wrought in the Trenches; but the <hi>French</hi> were repulſed, and ſeveral of them Slain, and the Beſiegers Works were ſtill carried on a Hundred and Fifty Paces farther. On the Beſiegers ſide Four Men were Slain out-right, and Twelve Wounded, among whom, Colonel <hi>Seymor</hi>'s Major, and one Captain. 'Twas ſaid that Marſhal <hi>Bouflers</hi> deſign'd to have taken the advantage of that Sally, and to have forc'd his way out with his Horſe, but that finding the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers had ſo well poſted their Troops to receive him, he thought it not convenient to put his Deſign in Execution at that time.</p>
            <p>The 15th the Beſiegers made a new Trench of about Three Hundred Paces in the Plain of <hi>Salſine,</hi> behind the other which they had raiſed before; and ran a Line from their Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as far as the old Trench at the Foot of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, to ſecure themſelves againſt Sallies. During which time, the Enemy were ſo thrifty of their Firing, that the Beſiegers had only Five or Six Men Wounded.</p>
            <p>The 16th the Beſiegers advanc'd their Trench in the Plain of <hi>Salſine,</hi> and enlarged and mended that at the Foot of the Mountain, which had been much endamag'd by the Rain.</p>
            <p>The 17th they advanc'd their Trench at the Foot of the Hill, above a Hundred Paces, and carried on that in the Plain of <hi>Salſine,</hi> in order to meet it. The next Night the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98680:16"/>Enemy fir'd thick and three-fold with their Small-ſhot and Great Guns, and made Two Sallies to diſturb the Pioneers; but were preſently beaten in again; Ten private Soldiers being Kill'd out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and a Colonel who commanded in the Trenches, and ſome others being Wounded.</p>
            <p>Upon the 28th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> about Eleven a Clock at Night, the Enemy made a Sally with about 200 Dragoons Mounted, and 500 Granadiers. The Firſt made an Onſet upon the Right Hand, with 160 Granadiers, where they were ſoon repuls'd by the Count of <hi>Ribera,</hi> who was viſiting the Night Poſts. After that, they made an Attack upon the Left Hand, where the Lord <hi>Cutts</hi> had poſted his advanc'd Guards to ſecure the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; at what time a Hundred Dragoons came upon Lieutenant <hi>Sutton,</hi> a Lieutenant of Colonel <hi>Seymor</hi>'s Regiment, who being poſted in the Plain of <hi>Salſine,</hi> with 35 Fuſiliers, ſuffer'd 'em to advance within a few Paces of him, and then diſcharging all his Fire upon 'em, retreated to his main Body; after which, the Dragoons preſſing hard upon him, he gave 'em a Second Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley; at what time the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Bavarian</hi> Horſe, who were poſted in the Plain of <hi>Salſine</hi> to ſecond the Infantry, fell in pell mell with the Enemy, and purſu'd 'em to the very gate of the Caſtle. In which Action, the Enemy confeſs'd that they had one half of their Dragoons kill'd, together with the Officer that commanded them.</p>
            <p>Upon the 25th, came Letters to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> that His Majeſty having receiv'd Information, that <hi>Villeroy</hi> was upon a full March to <hi>Fleurus,</hi> thought it convenient to leave the Camp before <hi>Namur</hi> to the Conduct of the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein Pleon,</hi> and join the Army commanded by the Prince of <hi>Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demont,</hi> taking up his Quarters at <hi>Boneſee</hi> near <hi>Mazy.</hi> The next Day the Enemy made a Halt at <hi>Fleurus,</hi> being joyn'd by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment from <hi>Germany,</hi> and the other Troops commanded by the Count <hi>de Harcourt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Evening of the ſame Day, the <hi>French</hi> marched to <hi>Gem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blours,</hi> and ſeem'd to prepare themſelves for a pitch'd Battel, for they leſt their Tents, and advanc'd toward the King of <hi>England,</hi> as near as the Ground would permit. Upon which His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty drew out his Army, with a Reſolution to engage. And
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98680:17"/>in that poſture the whole Army continu'd all that Day; his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſtaying in the Field in Perſon, from Four a Clock in the Morning, till Eight in the Evening; in which condition the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates</hi> ſtood ready to receive the Enemy, whenever they thought it convenient to begin.</p>
            <p>And it ſeem'd that <hi>Villeroy</hi> had either a real intent to relieve the Beſieged, or elſe to try what a Bravado would do. For he caus'd ſeveral Pieces of Canon to be diſcharg'd, which were ſuppos'd to be a Signal, and which were anſwer'd by the Beſieged with Lights from the Higheſt part of the Caſtle. In the mean time, the Works before the Caſtle went on very well, and the Canon had made great Breaches as well in the Caſtle as <hi>Coehorn,</hi> inſomuch that all the Diſcourſe was of a General Aſſault.</p>
            <p>Upon the 29th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> came an Expreſs from his Majeſties Camp to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> giving an Account, That a General Storm had been made upon the Caſtle of <hi>Namur,</hi> that ſtill it held out, which Aſſault was order'd in the following manner. The Lord <hi>Cutts</hi> was appointed to attack the Counterſcarp and Breach of the <hi>Terra Nova,</hi> with a Detachment of Granadiers, and 4 Regiments of Infantry. Count <hi>Rivera,</hi> a Major General in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Service, was order'd to ſtorm the <hi>Coehorn</hi> Fort, on that ſide next the <hi>Terra Nova,</hi> with 3000 <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Bavarians;</hi> M. General <hi>la Cave,</hi> was aſſign'd to attack the <hi>Coehorn</hi> on the Right Hand of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> with 2000 <hi>Brandenburghers,</hi> while M. Gen. <hi>Swering</hi> attack'd the <hi>Caſotte</hi> with 2000 <hi>Dutch</hi> Infantry, and another Colonel at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack'd the Lower Town with about 2000 Men more.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> advanc'd with great Order and Reſolution, and had gain'd the top of the Breach, forcing their way through Fire and Smoke on every ſide; but they found the Enemy ſo advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagiouſly poſted and entrench'd behind the Breach, and the Ground on their ſide ſo very bad, that they could not get Ground in front, but were forc'd to retire.</p>
            <p>Count <hi>Rivera</hi> was Slain among the foremoſt, upon their firſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to the <hi>Coehorn;</hi> however the <hi>Bavarians</hi> poſted themſelves upon a Saliant Angle of the Counterſcarp, and kept firing fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly upon the Enemy, who endeavour'd with great Obſtinacy to diſlodge them: Inſomuch, that when moſt of the Officers of the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Guards were kill'd and Wounded, and that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98680:17"/>Regiments had ſuffered great Damage, the Enemy ſtill firing with a more than ordinary Reſolution, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> who had quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Terra Nova,</hi> as not being able to do any good on that ſide, ſeconded the <hi>Bavarians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> under the Command of the Lord <hi>Cutts,</hi> who at the ſame time having order'd a Lieutenant of Colonel <hi>Mackay</hi>'s Regiment, with 30 Men, to break through the Paliſados, and attack a Battery of the Enemies; the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant executed his Orders with that undaunted Bravery, that he turn'd Seven of the Enemies Canon againſt themſelves, and at the ſame inſtant ſecur'd ſome of their Mines; by which means the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Bavarians</hi> planted their Colours upon the Paliſados, and made a good Lodgment.</p>
            <p>In the mean time M. Gen. <hi>la Cave,</hi> with his <hi>Brandenburghers,</hi> and M. Gen. <hi>Swering</hi> with his <hi>Dutch-men,</hi> made each of them Two other Lodgments, of which the Beſiegers continu'd in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and preſently fell to work to improve them, in order to another Aſſault; and the Batteries were order'd to play afreſh upon the <hi>Terra Nova,</hi> to make the Breach wider, and facilitate a 2d Attack.</p>
            <p>In this Action, the Loſs that fell upon the Four <hi>Engliſh</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, who made the Aſſault, was as follows.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Cutts</hi> Wounded.</p>
            <p>Nineteen Commiſſion Officers kill'd, and Fifty Four Wounded.</p>
            <p>Private Soldiers 339. Slain outright; 682 Wounded; Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers Wounded, Col. <hi>Windſor,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thompſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stanhope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other Advice from His Majeſties Camp at <hi>Oſtin, Sept.</hi> 1. N.S. gave a farther Account, that during theſe Tranſactions, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my appear'd every Day in the Front of the Confedrates Line; that on the <hi>Tueſday</hi> before, they came with about 70 Squadrons to <hi>Boneff,</hi> extending their Line from that Place, to the Right Hand, near <hi>Perwys.</hi> Upon which, his Majeſty order'd the Confederate Army to move, extending his Right Wing to <hi>Longchamp,</hi> and his Left to St. <hi>Denis;</hi> and leaving a Brigade of <hi>Maſy</hi> to ſecure that Poſt. The laſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> they appear'd with about Eleven Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons near the Advanc'd Guard, but were ſoon repuls'd.</p>
            <p>The next day his Majeſty having din'd Early, and in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon being upon the Road, returning to the Siege, in order to give Directions for a ſecond Attack of the Caſtle, was met by an Adjutant ſent by the D. of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> to inform his Majeſty
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98680:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>that M. <hi>Bouflers</hi> and the Count <hi>de Guiſcard</hi> had deſir'd to Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; that they had offer'd at firſt to treat for <hi>Coehorn</hi> Fort alone, but that being refus'd 'em by the Elector, they had agreed to capitulate for the whole.</p>
            <p>Thereupon, ſo ſoon as his Majeſty was arriv'd, Hoſtages were exchang'd, and Propoſals brought from the Caſtle to the <hi>Salſine;</hi> the Enemy inſiſted at firſt, that they might have Ten Days time to expect Succour, but that was abſolutely refus'd 'em; for it was plain, that the Enemy had ſuffer'd very much in the laſt Aſſault, and that they were extreamly diſcourag'd by their Loſſes.</p>
            <p>So that at length upon the 2d of <hi>September,</hi> N. S. in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Capitulation for the Surrender of the Caſtle of <hi>Namur</hi> was Sign'd, and the Beſiegers took the poſſeſſion of part of the Outworks; upon which <hi>Villeroy</hi> began to draw off, and retire with the <hi>French</hi> Army toward <hi>Flerus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Subſtance of the Capitulation was,</p>
            <q>
               <p>That the Outward Fortifications, that is to ſay the Fort of <hi>Coehorn,</hi> the Redoubt <hi>Caſemate,</hi> the Hornwork of <hi>Bale,</hi> and the <hi>Caſotte</hi> ſhould be delivered up the 2d Inſtant by nine in the morning.</p>
               <p>That the Garriſon ſhould march out with Drums beating, Colours flying, two pieces of Cannon <hi>24;</hi> two <hi>12;</hi> and two <hi>6</hi> Pounders, two Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and this upon the 5th Inſtance in the morning.</p>
               <p>That they ſhould be provided with Horſes and Wagons ſufficient for tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of their Equipage, and ſuch of the Sick and Wounded as are able to depart with the Garriſon, and that the Beſieged might leave Officers and Commiſſaries to take care of the reſt.</p>
               <p>That no Officers ſhall be ſtopp'd for Money lent, or Goods deliver'd, provided they give Security, or Hoſtages for ſatisfaction of what they might owe.</p>
               <p>That no ſatisfaction ſhould be demanded for Houſes demoliſhed during the Siege, but that Cattel and Horſes taken in the County of <hi>Namur</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Siege, ſhall be paid for.</p>
               <p>All Magazines to be faithfully deliver'd up.</p>
               <p>All Mines to be faithfully diſcover'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Of this <hi>Capitulation,</hi> Two Copies were Sign'd, One by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> the other by Marſhal <hi>de Bouflers,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>de Guiſcard.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
